Guide to the Time Inc. Records Overview 1853-2015 MS 3009
New-York Historical Society
Records groups from the business and publishing side of Time Inc. may include files from a magazine's publishers, business managers, general managers, and advertising, promotion, and circulation departments. Of note are the Advertising Promotion and Circulation Promotion Files assembled by the Time Inc. Archives and containing records and mailings from the advertising promotion and circulation promotion departments of many Time Inc. publications. Additional records on the marketing of the magazines are in the Consumer Marketing Records.
Other business and publishing records groups include Time Publishing and Business Records; Fortune Publishing and Business Records; People Publishing and Business Records; Life Publishing and Business Records; Discover Publishing and Business Records; TV-Cable Week Publishing and Business Records; and Sports Illustrated Publishing and Business Records. The Time Inc. Invitational Records document an annual invitation-only sporting event organized by the magazines' Advertising Sales Departments and held to foster relationships with advertisers. The Time Inc. Postal Rates Records document Time Inc. advocating for its position on postal rates for mailing publications.
Record groups that cover Time Inc.'s forays beyond magazine publishing include the Time-Life News Service Records documenting Time Inc.'s news gathering and reporting service; the The March of Time with files on production of the radio, film, and television versions; the Books Group Records documenting Time Inc.'s ventures in book publishing and book and gift subscription services; the Video Group Records documenting Time Inc.'s work in the cable, film, and television industries including records from Time-Life Films, Time-Life Broadcast, and Home Box Office (HBO); the New Media Records documenting the management of Time Inc.'s internet projects; sales data from music record labels managed by Time Warner Entertainment; and newspaper company records from the previous owner of a newspaper acquired by Time Inc.
Record groups regarding subsidiaries of Time Inc. include the Printing Developments, Inc. containing business expense ledgers and payroll books; the Time Canada Ltd. Records regarding the subsidiary that published the Canadian edition of Time; and Selling Areas-Marketing, Inc. (SAMI) which produced reports on the sale of consumer goods and offered them for sale by subscription.
This Guide is an overview of the portion of the archive that is processed and open to researchers. Further summary of the content is found in the Container List. More detailed description of the content is included in the Guides for the individual record groups that constitute the archive. Researchers with inquiries that appear to fall outside the scope of this material should contact the Curator of Manuscripts.
Bibliography
Elson, Robert T., and Duncan Norton-Taylor. 1973. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1941-1960. New York: Atheneum.
Prendergast, Curtis, and Geoffrey Colvin. 1986. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Changing Enterprise, 1960-1980. New York: Atheneum.
Elson, Robert T. 1968. Time, Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1923-1941. New York: Atheneum.
American periodicals -- History; Corporation records.; Corporations -- History.; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Journalists -- United States.; Mass media -- United States; Organization files.; Periodicals -- Publishing.; Photojournalists -- United States.; Printing industry; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Publishers and publishing -- United States -- History; Time, inc. -- Archives; Time, inc. -- History
- RG 1. Time Inc. Subject Files (1889-2015)
  Scope and Contents Note
  The Subject Files document the history of Time Inc. as an organization and have information on each publication and many departments at Time Inc. The Time Inc. Archives originally assembled and arranged the Subject Files for use by writers and researchers working on three authorized volumes of Time Inc. history. This record group contains primary documents from throughout the company and contains the majority of early records. Frequent subjects include corporate, editorial, and publishing. Corporate covers the acquisition and sale of entities as well as contracts and agreements between organizations, negotiations, board meetings, and other similar business relations. Editorial or Edit relates to the work being done by correspondents, reporters, and researchers. Publishing includes everything from advertising and promotion to production and circulation.
  Additional records on the divisions, departments and offices at Time Inc. are in the Time Inc. Reference Files (MS 3009-RG 3) and the Time Inc. Annex Files (MS 3009-RG 39).
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Subject Files.
- RG 2. Time Inc. Bio Files (1907-2015)
  The Time Inc. Bio Files were assembled and maintained by the Time Inc. Archives and predominately document the careers of Time Inc. staff from board members (H. P. Davison) and company executives (John S. Martin, Ray Cave, Hedley Donovan, Elizabeth Valk Long) to administrative assistants. The files represent staff from all divisions, departments and subsidiaries including Time, Life, Fortune, Sports Illustrated, Architectural Forum, March of Time, Time-Life Books, Time-Life Films, Time-Life International, Home Box Office, Little, Brown and Company, and Inland Container Company. Time Inc. also kept files on non-staff closely associated with the company, and some family and former classmates of cofounders Henry R. Luce and Briton Hadden in relation to interviews during various history and biography projects.
  This record group also includes the collection's primary files on cofounder Hadden, the majority of records from second Time Inc. president Roy E. Larsen, and very early corporate records in board member H. P. Davison's files.
  Contents consist of correspondence; memoranda regarding new hires, departing staff and other staffing changes; press releases; news clippings including obituaries; articles from the staff newsletters; articles or correspondent cables by or about staff; reports and comments on articles and books under consideration for publication; invitations to events; and speeches or other public remarks. Photographs and other photographic material, and audiovisual recordings of interviews, oral histories, and public speeches are present infrequently.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Bio Files.
- RG 3. Time Inc. Reference Files (1907-2015)
  The Time Inc. Reference Files document the history of various Time Inc. divisions such as the editing and publishing groups for the major titles, Circulation, various office locations, and Public Affairs; franchises such as the Sports Illustrated "Swimsuit Issue" and Time "Person of the Year" (originally "Man of the Year"); and staff organizations. While the Reference Files seem to serve a similar purpose to the Time Inc. Subject Files, this record group may have, at one point, been organically created by departments sending copies of informative records to Time Inc.'s "central file."
  Specific items of interest in this collection include the Department Head Lists, which record the structure of the company and names and titles of top-level staff; and copies of FYI, an internal Time Inc. staff newsletter which discuss department and staffing changes, events and milestones, along with a card index of the contents.
  Additional records on the divisions, departments and offices at Time Inc. are in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1) and the Time Inc. Annex Files (MS 3009-RG 39).
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Reference Files.
- RG 4. Time Inc. Index Cards (1933-1993)
  The Time Inc. Index Cards contain groups of index cards used by Time Inc. staff for writing, searching, and cross referencing subject terms in Time Inc.'s major magazines, and as directories for published books and interviews.The majority of index cards provide a subject term, a brief description of a topic, and a date when the topic was covered within the associated magazine. There is also a section of general subjects that is not linked to a specific publication.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Index Cards.
- RG 5. Time Inc. Corporate Administration Records (1853-2002)
  The Corporate Administration Records contain files from the corporate-level offices and executives of Time Inc. Executives and offices represented include the president, chief executive officer, chairman of the board, and chairman of the executive committee; corporate secretary; the finance division including files from the treasurer and investor relations; executive vice presidents; vice presidents overseeing administration, international, communications, and newspaper acquisitions; and a director of international business. Staff represented include Roy E. Larsen, James A. Linen, Andrew Heiskell, Ralph P. Davidson, Reginald K. Brack, Jr., and Don Logan.
  Records document corporate strategic planning for Time Inc., corporate filings, investments in terms of Time Inc. shareholders or in regards to employee retirement accounts, and major acquisitions, sales, or mergers including the merger between Time Inc. and Warner Communications creating Time Warner. Records also include executive committee minutes, five-year plans, notary seals, patents owned by Time Inc., early printing agreements, and corporate books or other organizational records from affiliates and subsidiaries of Time Inc.
  Further additions to this record group are expected.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Corporate Administration Records.
- RG 6. Time Inc. Corporate Editorial Records (1944-1998)
  The Time Inc. Corporate Editorial Records contain records from editorial staff working at the corporate level overseeing all publications at Time Inc. Executive offices, including the top editorial staff, were located on the 34th floor in the Time & Life Building. Staff represented include Editors-in-Chief Hedley Donovan, Henry Grunwald, and Jason McManus; Editorial Directors Ralph Graves, Ray Cave, and Richard Stolley; Corporate Editors McManus, Gilbert Rogin, and James Gaines; Assistant Corporate Editor David Maness; and Special Assistant Rogin. Records include appointment books; departmental and subject files; internal and external correspondence; speeches; and travel information.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Corporate Editorial Records.
- RG 7. Time Inc. Time Editorial Records (1938-2009)
  Scope and Contents
  The Time Editorial Records contain records from offices and staff from the editorial side of the magazine, not the publishing or business side. Staff represented include Managing Editors Otto Fuerbringer and James R. Gaines, Executive Editors Dana Tasker and Edward Jamieson, Art Department Cover Researcher Rosemary Frank, and art and culture journalist Rosalind Constable. Records include internal and external correspondence; departmental and subject files; cover artist files; speeches; travel itineraries; personnel files; files and reports from the Letters Department; and collected research for elections reporting.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Time Editorial Records.
- RG 8. Time Inc. Fortune Editorial Records (1951-2013)
  The Fortune Editorial Records contain materials from the offices and staff of the editorial side of the magazine, not the publishing or business side. Staff represented in this record group include managing editor Robert Lubar, managing editor Louis Banks, managing editor Duncan Nortan-Taylor, managing editor Andrew Serwer, staff writer Charles Burck, and staff writer Rush Loving Jr. Also included are materials from the Art Department on planning and creating issues in 1982 and files on staff, freelance writers, and other contributors to Fortune.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Fortune Editorial Records.
- RG 9. Time Inc. Life Editorial Records (1937-2013)
  The Life Editorial Records include files from offices and staff that produced both the original version of Life and the revived monthly version. The Managing Editors (ME) begin with the last ME of the original Life. Other staff included are one Executive Editor; two Senior Editors, one from the original Life and one from the revived version; two staff photographers, with Alfred Eisenstaedt being one of the original hires at the launch of the magazine; and one staff writer. Records include business correspondence, interoffice memoranda, letters from readers, drafts of articles, audiovisual interviews and oral histories, article proposals, and magazine and corporate policies.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Life Editorial Records.
- RG 10. Time Inc. People Editorial Records (1966-1989)
  The People Editorial Records contain records from offices and staff from the editorial side of the magazine, not the publishing or business side. Editorial staff represented include Cranston Jones, Lee Wohlfert, Marianne Macy, Martha Babcock, Sarah Rozen, Richard Stolley, and Dick Lemon.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. People Editorial Records.
- RG 11. Time Inc. Money Editorial Records: Managing Editor Marshall Loeb Files (1981-1986)
  The Time Inc. Money Editorial Records: Managing Editor Marshall Loeb Files focus on public appearances made by Loeb while he was managing editor. The collection is primarily scripts and transcripts.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Money Editorial Records: Managing Editor Marshall Loeb Files.
- RG 12. Time Inc. Architectural Forum and House & Home Editorial Records: Managing Editor Edgar P. Smith Files (1952-1962)
  Contains Edgar P. Smith's records regarding the evaluation and possible sale of Architectural Forum and House & Home. Architectural Forum was a professional journal focused on design and modern architecture, and House & Home was a trade magazine for building and buying new houses.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Architectural Forum and House & Home Editorial Records: Managing Editor Edgar P. Smith Files.
- RG 13. Time Inc. Time Research Center Files (1919-2015)
  The Time Research Center Files contain research materials collected by Time Inc. reporters, researchers, and library staff in the main areas of Bio Files, Presidents Files, and Subject Files. Many of the files originally belonged to a Time Inc. reference library known throughout the years as The Morgue, The Bureau of Editorial Reference, and The Editorial Reference Library. The majority of research and reference materials are magazine and newspaper clippings. Other types of material include telegrams and other correspondence, correspondent dispatches, transcripts of interviews and speeches, editorial outlines for articles, editorial policies, press releases, and drafts of articles.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Time Research Center Files.
- RG 14. Time Inc. Time-Life News Service Records (1935-1987)
  The Time-Life News Service Records documents the management and activities of Time Inc.'s news gathering branch. While the department was formally part of Time magazine for most of its history, it gathered and reported on news for other magazines as well. The collection contains records from the chiefs of correspondents and their office, records from the New York Regional Bureau Chief, financial records, personnel and biographical files assembled on employees of the Time-Life News Service, dispatches and article research material that did not end up in the Time Research Center, and correspondence discussing masthead changes concerning Time-Life News Service staff. Due to overlap of financial management between the Time magazine business office and Time-Life New Service's financial office, financial records include Time budgets as well as financial documents for Time Inc. subsidiaries such as the Washington Star.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Time-Life News Service Records.
- RG 15. Time Inc. The March of Time Audiovisual Collection (1979-1995)
  The March of Time Audiovisual Collection contains internal and commercially distributed audiovisual materials that were produced by The March of Time, a division of Time Inc. The majority of records from The March of Time along with the material regarding its history can be found in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1) and Time Inc. Annex Files (MS 3009-RG 39).
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. The March of Time Audiovisual Collection.
- RG 16. Time Inc. New Building Department Records (1953-1967)
  The New Building Department Records contain the decisionmaking and planning files for the construction of Time Inc.'s new office space, the Time & Life Building, which is part of Rockefeller Center. Series I contains the chronological binders kept by the head of the department Henry "Hank" Luce III. Series II contains other materials created by the department during the planning period. Series III contains invoices and purchase orders for construction, interior decor, and furniture.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. New Building Department Records.
- RG 17. Time Inc. Human Resources and Personnel Records (1939-1989)
  The Time Inc. Human Resources and Personnel Records document employee relations, benefits, participation in unions, and Time Inc.'s efforts to create or implement personnel policies and guidelines.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Human Resources and Personnel Records.
- RG 18. Time Inc. Staff Organizations (1940-2015)
  Time Inc. Staff Organizations contains records from clubs, sports, and other membership organizations involving only Time Inc. staff. The organizations include the Time Inc. Bowling League, Lesbians and Gay Men at Time Warner (LGTW), and the Time-Life Alumni Society (TLAS). Further additions to this finding aid are expected.
  Click here to link to the Guide to Time Inc. Staff Organizations.
- RG 19. Time Inc. Corporate Public Affairs Department Records (1945-2000)
  Corporate Public Affairs Department Records contain the office files from Vice President Donald Wilson; files and correspondence from Louis Slovinsky while he was the the public relations manager, associate director, and director of public affairs; office files from the Radio/TV Publicity Office, project files from Community Relations; office files from the Chief Speechwriter; office files from the Special Events Manager; files on exhibitions in the Time & Life Building public spaces; files on exhibitions and contests to promote Time Inc. internationally; and general files produced or collected by the department overall including annual reports, press releases, dinner books, weekly news clippings, and administrative files.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Corporate Public Affairs Department Records.
- RG 20. Time Inc. News Clippings (1999-2013)
  The Time Inc. News Clippings contain copies of news articles about Time Warner and AOL Time Warner, its publications, and its subsidiaries collected by the Time Inc. Library and Archives. Corporate Communications compiled some of the clippings packets.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. News Clippings.
- RG 21. Time Inc. Advertising Promotion and Circulation Promotion Files (1922-2004)
  The Time Inc. Advertising Promotion and Circulation Promotion Files were assembled by the Time Inc. Archives and contain records from the advertising promotion and circulation promotion departments of many Time Inc. publications, including Fortune, Life, and Time.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Advertising Promotion and Circulation Promotion Files.
- RG 22. Time Inc. Printing Developments, Inc. (1950-1974)
  Contains the business ledgers of this Time Inc. subsidiary.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Printing Developments, Inc.
- RG 23. Time Inc. Real Estate Division Records (1960-1980)
  The Time Inc. Real Estate Division Records include files on building and land purchases, construction, and alternations for offices, laboratories, warehouses, and other facilities of Time Inc. and its subsidiaries.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Real Estate Division Records.
- RG 24. Time Inc. Time Publishing and Business Records (1927-1999)
  The Time Publishing and Business Records contain materials from the offices and staff of the business and publishing side of the magazine's operation. The majority of materials come from the office of the business manager; departments in charge of advertisements in the magazine; an educational materials subscription program; and public affairs.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Time Publishing and Business Records.
- RG 25. Time Inc. Fortune Publishing and Business Records (1929-2005)
  The Fortune Publishing and Business Records contain materials from the offices and staff of the business and publishing side of the magazine's operation. The majority of materials come from the offices of public affairs and promotions as well as from the office of Publisher William Geer. Records include clippings, correspondence, notes, transcripts, drafts, press releases, press kits, photographs, video cassettes, audio cassettes, and open audio reels.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Fortune Publishing and Business Records.
- RG 26. Time Inc. Life Publishing and Business Records (1936-2001)
  The Life Publishing and Business Records contain materials from the offices and staff of the business and publishing side of the magazine's operation. The majority of materials come from the publisher, business office, market research, and circulation departments.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Life Publishing and Business Records.
- RG 27. Time Inc. People Publishing and Business Records (1973-2003)
  With the first issue launched on on March 4, 1974, People was one of the first publications coming out of the Magazine Development Group later transitioning into its own department. The People Publishing and Business Records contain records from offices and staff from the publishing and business side of the magazine, not the editorial side. Staff represented include Publisher Richard Durrell, Assistant Publisher Charlotte Schiff-Jones, Associate Consumer Marketing Director John Hartig, Director of Marketing Services Chuck Lund, and Magazine Development Group Marketing Director Mal Ochs.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. People Publishing and Business Records.
- RG 28. Time Inc. Books Group Records (1963-1988, 2015)
  The Time Inc. Books Group Records contain materials documenting Time Inc.'s book publishing ventures. While Time-Life Books was Time Inc.'s main imprint and book publishing department, Time Inc. owned several other book publishing, subscription, or direct marketing ventures and companies including Little, Brown and Company and the Book-of-the-Month Club. Included in this record group are files from the office of the group vice president, the Books and Arts Associates, the Iran Publishing Project, and the Time-Life Travel Club.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Books Group Records.
- RG 29. Time Inc. Invitational Records (1982-1989)
  The Time Inc. Invitational was an annual invitation-only sports competition event organized by the magazines' Advertising Sales Departments and held at the Maidstone Club in East Hamptons, NY. Records include the planning and event materials for the years 1983 to 1985, 1987, and 1989.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the Time Inc. Invitational Records.
- RG 31. Time Inc. Annual Reports (1922-2016)